Jake, you're hardly touching
your salad.
I promised Berta I'd cut down
on the roughage.
Well, all right, ahem,
why don't I get the soup?
Based on the salad,
I'm not so optimistic.
So you have absolutely no idea
why she invited us here?
- All she said on the phone was dinner.
- You believed her?
Good God, man,
do you realize what you've done?
- Just relax.
- Just relax?
We'll be lucky to leave here
with all of our limbs and gonads.
- What's a gonad?
- You are.
So it's bad.
- You're not a gonad.
- Says the other gonad.
Here we go.
Potato leek soup.
Oh, delightful.
You got any crackers?
Crackers?
I like having something crunchy
in my soup.
Little goldfish, crouton, a stale bagel.
I'll check. Go ahead and start.
Captain Crunch will work in a pinch.
I got a bad feeling about this, Alan.
- What? We're having dinner with our mother.
- So you feel it too.
What kind of person
doesn't serve crackers with soup?
The only thing I have that's crunchy
is macadamia nuts.
Interesting. Let's give her a try.
Well, I suppose you boys
are wondering why I asked you here.
You mean, this isn't just a nice,
warm family dinner?
Knock it off, Charlie.
I have some good news.
And no, I'm not dying.
I didn't say anything.
Why would you even go there?
Okay, I'm sorry.
Anyway, I have been doing
some financial planning.
So you're thinking about dying.
Trust me, darling, I promise
to stick around long enough...
...to identify your bloated, gin-soaked,
syphilitic remains.
Okay, so we got a time frame.
So, what about your financial plan?
Yes, well, ahem, one thing I've done
is to set aside enough money...
...to ensure that my grandson
will get a college education.
Oh, Mom, Mom, that is, uh,
that is very generous...
...but, uh, I started a college fund
for Jake when he was born.
Really?
How much do you have in there now?
Uh.
Did you hear?
Grandma's sending you to college.
Now? I haven't finished my soup.
Mom, have you thought this through?
Look at him.
Maybe there should be one child
left behind.
Charlie, Charlie, just shush.
Mo-- Mom, I cannot tell you
how much I appreciate this.
Jake, do you understand
what your grandma is providing here?
Yeah, more school. Big whoop.
Well, Jake, dear,
perhaps this will help enthuse you.
If, If you buckle down
and your grades improve...
...when the time comes for you
to go to college...
...Grandmommy
is going to buy you a new car.
I love you, Grandmommy.
When I get my car from Grandma...
...one of you guys
is gonna have to park on the street.
The car is for college.
And what makes you think
you'll still be here?
Oh, come on, you know you love me.
He's got you. You do love him.
Yeah, but he doesn't have
to rub my nose in it.
So, what do you think Mom's angle is?
Does she have to have an angle?
A college trust fund? For him?
Last week, he bit his hand
eating a sandwich.
He smelled the ham, he got excited.
Maybe she's just trying to buy his love.
[SlGHS]
Alan, think it through. She could've done
that with a pork chop and a Creamsicle.
Whatever, it is a big load off my mind
knowing his education is taken care of.
Oh, yeah, that's what Mom wants,
to take a load off your mind.
Okay, why do you think she did it?
I don't know.
But if you wanna get inside her head...
...you've gotta start thinking
more twisted, manipulative, devious.
For example...
...if by some miracle,
he gets through college...
- ...and she sends him to law school--
- Law school? You've already lost me.
Maybe she's boinking Dean of Admissions.
We don't know. Just hear me out.
Go on.
Let's say he crawls through law school...
...takes seven or eight shots at the bar.
We know how that ends.
So, what are his options
as a failed lawyer?
I don't know. Government work?
Exactly. Maybe he lands
on the zoning commission.
And bingo-bango, Mom finally gets
to put a second story on her house.
You really think she's gonna send him
to college and law school...
...just so she can add an extra bedroom?
That's insane.
Is it, Alan?
Is it really?
Morning.
- Alan?
- Yeah?
You having a stroke?
No. No, I'm just--
I'm just trying to figure out...
...why I need to go to work today.
I mean, Mom's taking care
of Jake's education, buying him a car.
Why should I bust my hump?
For your self-respect?
No. Judith got that in the divorce.
Because you like
to heal people's back pain...
...with your chiropractic magic?
[SNORTS]
Okay, well, you gotta go somewhere.
Why?
Because you're creeping me out.
I should take up motivational speaking.
- Morning.
- Something's wrong with your brother.
We don't say the word "wrong,"
we say "special."
No, it's true. My friends don't think
you're my grandma...
...they think you're my young aunt.
If he gets his nose further up
her keister...
...we're gonna have to tie a rope
to his feet.
Hey, I was thinking, you know what
would be a nice, safe vehicle for me?
A used police car.
I don't know. I guess from the police.
She's buying lunkhead a car?
And a college education.
Ha, that makes sense
if it's a clown college...
...and the car seats 20.
All right, then I'll see you in an hour.
Hold on. No, I don't need one.
Okay, okay. Bye.
I'm gonna spend the afternoon with
Grandma. If she asks, I took a shower.
Figured out her angle yet?
No.
And that's what scares me.
BERTA:
Bom-bom-bom.
Seemed appropriate.
All right, Mr. Sharipa,
how's it feel right here?
SHARlPA:
A little tender.
Yeah, yeah,
you've got a spasm right there.
It's my own fault.
I was trying to do it in the shower
with Mrs. Sharipa last night.
The woman is no ballerina.
Well, sex in the shower
is really a young man's game.
Or a middle-aged man with a skinny wife.
- Sure.
- What can I say?
I like a little junk in the trunk.
I-- I think that says it.
Slap her on the ass at Christmas...
...it doesn't stop shaking
till New Year's Eve.
Just between you and me...
...uh, she enjoys a little spanking
from Santa.
Who doesn't?
I checked the list twice...
...always naughty.
Uh-huh. Could you, uh,
turn on your right, Mr. Sharipa?
I'll, uh, try to relieve the
pressure on your sciatic nerve.
Could you cross your arms, please?
Thank you.
Okay.
[FARTS]
Excuse me.
Oh, no, that-- That happens.
It's, uh, it's perfectly natu--
Oh, dear Lord.
Yeah, that's the garlic clams
I had for lunch.
I like them, they don't like me.
Um.
If you'll just excuse me for a moment.
Hey, you know, I feel better.
Maybe that's where the pressure
came from.
- Where are you going, Dr. Harper?
- Home.
Will you be coming back?
Dr. Harper?
Oh, my God.
Check it out. This SUV comes with
a mini-fridge in the glove compartment.
Fascinating.
Let's spend a little time
talking about our college plans.
Our plans? Are you going too?
Because that changes everything.
I've already been to college, darling.
They were some of the happiest years
of my life.
- Really?
- Mm-hm.
What kind of car did you have?
Look, Jake, I understand that
you're excited about getting a car...
...but keep in mind...
...the car is predicated
on you getting into college.
Right.
What's predicated mean?
No college, no car.
Oh.
What if I flunk out?
Do I have to give the car back?
Oh, sweetheart,
what makes you think you'd flunk out?
Well, history.
Now there's a 60-60 chance I'm gonna
have to repeat the eighth grade.
Sixty-sixty, huh?
At least. It could be 70-40.
Well, we can rule out the lvy League.
- ls that good?
- For the lvy League.
You know, dear, maybe we're
going about this the wrong way.
College should be about
pursuing the things you love.
Well, what do you love?
Um, TV, video games, sleeping.
I love sleeping so much
sometimes I actually dream about it.
Okay, maybe I wasn't clear enough.
Oh, you know what I really love?
Twice-dipped French toast
with a sprinkling of orange zest.
- Orange zest?
- You scrape it from an orange peel.
It's what really makes my recipe work.
You have a recipe?
Yep. It kind of happened by accident.
I was making once-dipped
French toast, but I dropped it.
Lot of great discoveries are accidents,
like Thomas Edison and the telephone.
That wasn't Thomas.
- So you like to cook?
- Yeah, I love it.
Because, you know, I love to eat
and I love to surprise my mouth.
Well, you know, dear...
...what you are talking about
is becoming a chef...
...and there are schools for that...
...and the potential
to make a terrific living.
Do I get to wear
one of those poofy hats?
If you want to.
Cool. Then I guess I'll be a chef.
My grandson the chef.
I can live with that.
Know what I could drive if I was a chef?
The Oscar Meyer Weinermobile.
- Hey.
I got a kayak.
I see.
Guess what I'm gonna do?
Go kayaking?
Yep. I have decided that life is too short.
So you're going out in
the Pacific Ocean in a plastic boat.
Good thinking.
No, I was at work today and it suddenly
became clear to me that--
[THUDS]
Oh, sorry about that.
It became clear to me
that I don't like what I'm doing.
Mom's taking care of Jake...
...I can spend my time doing things
that give me joy.
So you're gonna masturbate in a kayak?
No, but that's the point.
You'll have to elaborate.
I could, if I wanted to.
Yeah, who could have seen that coming?
Look, I'm sorry.
Here you go. Grilled cheese
with Gouda, Swiss and monster.
You mean "Muenster."
No, that's an old TV show.
And they're called that because
they're monsters. This is a cheese.
Anyway, this sandwich
has heirloom tomatoes...
...smoked applewood bacon
on sourdough toast.
Where did you learn this?
Food Channel, foodchannel.com,
Food Channel on Demand...
...Food Channel Magazine.
And the school lunch lady.
Oh, and save room
for homemade potato chips.
You're making potato chips?
Oh, yeah, it's easy.
Slice the potatoes real thin,
rub the slices with lemon and garlic.
Fry them up in a hot iron skillet
and then salt to taste.
I can't get over this.
- Bon appetite.
- Mm.
- Teet.
- No, that's a cow's boob.
Oh, my goodness.
This is delicious.
Don't eat more than three
or you won't poop for a week.
Trust me.
Well, at least we have finally found
a career path for you.
Cool. I'll go get the chips
and we'll talk about cars.
You know what?
Let's settle this car thing first.
Oh, God, it was incredible.
The-- The wind, the sky, the surf.
Ah, I feel like I'm reborn.
You were out there for 15 minutes.
Yeah, well, my arms got tired.
Oh, so you did decide to go kayanking.
- What?
- Masturyaking.
You're terrible.
And anyway, no one could see me.
- So now what?
- Now?
Now I just live. I enjoy.
All right.
This rat has quit the race.
Good for you.
This hamster is off the treadmill.
Glad to hear it.
This squirrel is satisfied
with the nuts he has.
No comment.
[SlGHS]
I'm not gonna make it, Charlie.
Didn't think you would.
No goals...
...no challenges...
...no gut-wrenching fear
driving me forward.
I mean, how can you stand it?
Me?
Well, I have kind of an existential
philosophy that shapes my outlook.
It involves a willingness to let life
carry me along in its wake...
...as I contemplate
its infinite mystery.
Plus, I drink and take a lot of naps.
Yeah, well, I need something
meaningful to strive for.
Sorry, I don't follow.
I need a carrot in front of me
and a stick behind me. Without that l--
I have no reason to live.
- That's it.
- What's it?
No reason to live.
That's Mom's angle.
It's never had anything to do with Jake.
She's trying to kill you.
Oh, come on.
Think about it.
She takes the pressure
off your shoulders...
...knowing you can't live without it.
Oh, she's good.
Why would Mom wanna kill me?
I don't know. Why do I wanna kill you?
Why does your ex-wife wanna kill you?
You just bring that out in people.
You're being ridiculous.
Okay, okay,
let's look at the alternate explanation.
For the first time in her life,
our mother is being totally selfless...
...and thinking
about someone else's well-being.
Dear God,
my own mother is trying to kill me.
I'm glad we got that settled.
It was really bugging me.
[lNDlSTlNCT CHATTER OVER RADlO]
- Terrific sandwich.
FlREMAN: Yeah.
You'll find the fire gave everything
a nice smoky flavor.
Just out of curiosity,
what does a used firetruck go for?
Hey, Alan.
I got an idea that might cheer you up.
I'm listening.
You need a carrot and a stick
to make your life meaningful?
How about this?
Every month I let you give me
a small amount of money...
...in exchange for the pleasure
of living in my house.
We'll call it rent.
Wow, it's been a long time
since I paid rent.
Five years, two months, 11 days.
Interesting. It would certainly give me
a reason to go back to work.
Right, that's the carrot.
And if you fall behind,
I get to hit you with a stick.
- Very funny.
- No, I'm serious. That's my carrot.
Okay, how much did you have in mind?
Well, I've given it some thought...
...and I think you'll find this
to be a fair number.
Oh.
Oh, well, uh...
...if I'm paying rent, I'll get a say
in what goes on around here.
No, no, no.
If you want a say...
...this is the number.
I don't need a say.
- Good. So every month on the first?
- Deal.
All right. All right.
I feel good about this.
Pitching in, pulling my own weight.
It's long overdue.
Five years, two months, 11 days.
Right.
Uh, of course, since, uh,
the month has already started...
- ...we'll start next month.
- Fine.
Although, uh, with the holidays coming,
maybe it'd be better to start fresh...
...with the new year. One, one.
Sure, whatever.
- Unless the economy's still in the tank.
- Always a possibility.
In which case, we'll, uh, probably
wanna revisit the number.
CHARLlE:
Probably.
I mean, you know, the market is,
is pretty volatile right now.
Uh, I think some belt-tightening is in order
for everybody.
You know, landlords and tenants alike.
[THUD THEN ALAN SHOUTS]
[ENGLlSH SDH]